<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Quals Reading Notes</title>
    <description>Notes on readings for my qualifying exams.
</description>
    <link>http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2015 16:13:29 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2015 16:13:29 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Model based Bayesian exploration</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Dearden1999&quot;&gt;Dearden, R., Friedman, N., &amp;amp; Andre, D. (1999). Model based Bayesian exploration. &lt;i&gt;Proceedings Of the Fifteenth Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence&lt;/i&gt;, 150–159. Retrieved from http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2073814&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reinforcement learning (RL), there are two main approaches: &lt;em&gt;model-based RL&lt;/em&gt;, in which an explicit model of the transitions and/or rewards are estimated, and &lt;em&gt;model-free RL&lt;/em&gt;, in which this mdoel is not estimated and just the value of a state is estimated. In the model-based case, however, the estimated model is typically just a point estimate (e.g. a maximum-likelihood estimate) and thus does not reflect any uncertainty about the transition or reward model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, Dearden et al. suggest using &lt;em&gt;Bayesian model-based RL&lt;/em&gt; in which Bayesian inference is used to maintain a posterior distribution over the transition and reward models, thus capturing both an estimate of what the models are as well as confidence for how accurate that estimate is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;methods&quot;&gt;Methods&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;n/a&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;algorithm&quot;&gt;Algorithm&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The sequence of states and actions taken by the agent can be summarized as a sequence of &lt;em&gt;experience tuples&lt;/em&gt;, $\langle s, a, r, t \rangle$. The agent’s belief about the MDP (i.e. the true transition and reward functions) is $\mu$, so that $P(M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;\mu)$ is the agent’s prior over possible MDPs given their initial belief $\mu$. After one timestep, the agent has a new experience and the updated distribution can be written as:&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align*}
P(M|\mu \circ \langle s, a, r, t \rangle) &amp;\propto P(\langle s, a, r, t \rangle | M)P(M|\mu)
&amp;= P(s\rightarrow^a t|M)P(s\rightarrow^a r|M)P(M|\mu)
\end{align*} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can represent the particular transition and reward functions by sets of parameters $\theta^t_{s,a,t}$ and $\theta^r_{s,a,r}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a distribution over MDPs also induces a distribution over $Q$ functions. Rather than maximizing the $Q$ function directly, as is typically the case in RL, Dearden et al. choose actions which maximize:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;VPI(s,a)-(\max_{a^\prime}E[q_{s,a^\prime}]-E[q_{s,a}])&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $VPI$ is the &lt;em&gt;value of perfect information&lt;/em&gt;, which is essentially how much information we would get from taking action $a$ in state $s$. What this strategy basically says is that we should take actions which give us more information, but not if we think the $Q$-value of that action is low relative to the $Q$-value of the best current action. Thus, the tradeoff between exploration and exploitation is given explicitly in terms of information (though this is not actually information in the information-theoretic sense—they are using “gain” here to mean the expected difference in value if we think the action is the best, and learn that it isn’t; or that we think the action isn’t the best, and learn that it is).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;takeaways&quot;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dearden et al. go on to discuss various ways of approximating the $Q$ distribution, but I am not going to go into these specifics. I think the more important takeaway from this paper is the idea that you can perform Bayesian inference over the transition and reward functions and thus capture uncertainty about how accurate your estimate is.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2015 08:12:21 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/planning%20and%20decision%20making/2015/12/16/Dearden1999.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/planning%20and%20decision%20making/2015/12/16/Dearden1999.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Planning and decision making</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A survey of Monte Carlo Tree Search methods</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Browne2012&quot;&gt;Browne, C., Powley, E., Whitehouse, D., Lucas, S., Cowling, P. I., Rohlfshagen, P., … Colton, S. (2012). A survey of Monte Carlo tree search methods. &lt;i&gt;IEEE Transactions On Computational Intelligence and AI in Games&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;4&lt;/i&gt;(1), 1–10. doi:10.1109/TCIAIG.2012.2186810&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper gives a comprehensive overview of the Monte Carlo Tree Search (MCTS) algorithm and the variations thereof. In reading this paper, I am focusing less on the variations of the algorithm and just on the core ideas behind how it works, which are laid out in pages 1-10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic idea behind MCTS is to build up a tree, where each node corresponds to a state and each edge from a node corresponds to an action. Leaf nodes are chosen according to a particular algorithm, and then full games are simulated from those nodes until they terminate. Then, the results of the simulation are backpropagated up the tree all the way to the root node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;methods&quot;&gt;Methods&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;n/a&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;algorithm&quot;&gt;Algorithm&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic algorithm of MCTS is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Selection&lt;/em&gt;: start at the root node, and walk down the tree according to the “tree policy” until either an expandable node is reached or a terminal state is reached. A node is “expandable” if it has previously unexplored children.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Expansion&lt;/em&gt;: expand one of the child nodes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Simulation&lt;/em&gt;: run forward a simulation from the expanded child node until the simulation terminates according to some “default policy”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Backpropagation&lt;/em&gt;: update the statistics of all nodes in the path from the root node to the expanded child node based on the results of the simulation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These steps are repeated while there is still computation time remaining. Then, the action is taken that corresponds to the best child node of the root node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Browne et al. describe a tree policy called the &lt;em&gt;Upper Confidence Bound for Trees&lt;/em&gt; (UCT), which chooses a child node $j$ to maximize:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;UCT= \bar{X}_j + 2 C_p\sqrt{\frac{2\log n}{n_j}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where \widebar{X}_j is the average reward of child $j$, $n$ is the number of times the parent node has been visited, $n_j$ is the number of times child $j$ has been visited, and $C_p&amp;gt;0$ is a constant. When $n_j=0$, the second term will be infinite, and thus will cause unexplored children to be explored prior to exploiting nodes that have been explored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;takeaways&quot;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MCTS is a successful approach to dealing with large state/action spaces, which product deep trees with large branching factors. MCTS offers a way to trade off between exploration and exploitation while still being able to roll out simulations all the way to termination. This means that even if rewards are only acheived at the end (e.g., win or lose), they can still be incorporated. And, unlike other RL techniques, MCTS does not require that the full state space be enumerated, which may be necessary to fully estimate the value of a state in terms of its future rewards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some thoughts/questions that I have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How does MCTS work when rewards are asymmetric, e.g. in the case of a game where the goal is simply to keep playing for as long as possible? In this case, all terminal states would have a negative reward (for lose). I suppose you could perhaps give rewards that are instead equal to the length of the game that is played, but I’m not sure if that’s actually the correct approach.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sometimes the state/action space might not actually be a true tree, but just a DAG, because you can reach certain states in multiple ways. But, I think that MCTS would probably treat these states as separate and require that they be explored independently. This seems like it would be a waste of computation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2015 04:07:29 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/planning%20and%20decision%20making/2015/12/16/Browne2012.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/planning%20and%20decision%20making/2015/12/16/Browne2012.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Planning and decision making</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Concerning the perceptions in general</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Helmholtz1924&quot;&gt;Helmholtz, H. (1924). Concerning the perceptions in general. In J. P. C. Southall (Ed.), &lt;i&gt;Treatise on Physiological Optics&lt;/i&gt; (pp. 1–37). New York: Dover Publications.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helmholtz is often credited for explicitly stating that the goal of the mind is to infer what processes in the world give rise to our perceptions through a mechanism he terms “unconscious inference”. It could be that, in performing these unconscious inferences, we simply learn a series of associations between senses and things in the world. This would correspond, I suppose, to a discriminative view of perception. Helmholtz however doesn’t stop with associations, but goes further to assert that the way we perform unconscious inferences is by determining “generic notions” and “laws of nature”. In other words, our mind constructs a generative model of the world:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our intellect is the faculty of forming general conceptions. It has nothing to do with our sense-perceptions and experiences, unless it is able to form general conceptions or laws. These laws are then objectified and designated as causes. (pg. 34)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, this idea is almost &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the one put forth by &lt;a href=&quot;/quals/generative%20models/2015/11/11/Craik1943.html&quot;&gt;Craik&lt;/a&gt; about 50 years later:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My hypothesis then is that thought models, or parallels, reality—that its essential feature is not ‘the mind’, ‘the self’, ‘sense-data’, nor propositions but symbolism, and that this symbolism is largely of the same kind as that which is familiar to us in mechanical devices which aid thought and calculation (pg. 57)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the major difference between these two views is, perhaps, that Craik seems more committed to the idea that our mental models are exceedingly accurate, while Helmholtz doesn’t seem to care about their accuracy – they will be as accurate as the regularities in our perceptions lead us to believe. That is, if there is ambiguity in our perceptions, then our model of reality will be similarly ambiguous, lacking in detail, or inaccurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helmholtz also discusses the relevance of the &lt;em&gt;experiment&lt;/em&gt; in our ability to understand the world, foreshadowing approaches in active learning and optimal experiment design:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are not simply passive to the impressions that are urged on us, but we &lt;em&gt;observe&lt;/em&gt;, that is, we adjust our organs in those conditions that enable them to distinguish the impressions most accurately. (pg. 14)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also predicts the idea of thought as being symbolic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our ideas of things &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; be anything but symbols, natural signs for things which we learn how to use in order to regulate our movements and actions. Having learned correctly how to read those symbols, we are enabled by their help to adjust our actions so as to bring about the desired result; that is, so that the expected new sensations will arise. (pg. 19)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up, Helmholtz discusses a lot of the ideas that are really core to the way that we think about things today in cognitive science, and also to probabilistic, generative models of cognition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 10:17:11 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/generative%20models/2015/11/11/Helmholtz1924.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/generative%20models/2015/11/11/Helmholtz1924.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Generative models</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hypothesis on the nature of thought</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Craik1943&quot;&gt;Craik, K. (1943). Hypothesis on the nature of thought. In &lt;i&gt;The Nature of Explanation&lt;/i&gt; (pp. 50–61).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Craik was one of the first modern psychologists to explicitly propose the idea of having a generative model of the world. There are two main points that he makes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the mind uses a different representation than either sensory/motor inputs or outputs. There are “three essential processes” which consist of translation of external stimuli into symbols, processing of these symbols into other symbols, and retranslation of the new symbols into a new external representation (such as action).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, te way that we process symbols is by using a “model”, which he defines in relation to real, physical processes in the world. As in the famous quote that everybody likes to use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If the organism carries a ‘small-scale model’ of external reality and of its own possible actions within its head, it is able to try out various alternatives, conclude which is the best of them, react to future situations before they arise, utilise the knowledge of past events in dealing with the present and future, and in every way react in a much fuller, safer, and more competent manner to the emergencies which face it. (pg. 61)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Craik seems to think that such a model is more reliable than what it probably actually is (“we can, for instance, design a bridge in our minds and know that it will bear a train passing over it instead of having to conduct a number of full-scale experiments”, pg. 59), but the core idea is an important one. By having a model of reality, we can make predictions about reality that we otherwise wouldn’t be able to make, because reality is too complicated.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 10:17:11 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/generative%20models/2015/11/11/Craik1943.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/generative%20models/2015/11/11/Craik1943.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Generative models</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Speech recognition: a model and a program for research</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Halle1962&quot;&gt;Halle, M., &amp;amp; Stevens, K. N. (1962). Speech recognition: a model and a program for research. &lt;i&gt;IRE Transactions On Information Theory&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;8&lt;/i&gt;(2), 155–159. doi:10.1109/TIT.1962.1057686&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halle &amp;amp; Stevens were the first to propose the technique of “analysis-by-synthesis”. Actually, they did so even earlier, in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Halle1959&quot;&gt;Halle, M., &amp;amp; Stevens, K. M. (1959). Analysis by synthesis. In W. Wathen-Dunn &amp;amp; L. E. Woods (Eds.), &lt;i&gt;Proceedings of the Seminar of Speech Compression and Processing&lt;/i&gt; (Vol. 2).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, though, I have been unable to find this paper anywhere, but I assume that the present paper covers enough of the same ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halle &amp;amp; Stevens essentially make an argument for the “infinite use of finite means” (Chomsky, Humboldt), saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is then possible to store in the “permanent memory” of the analyzer only the rules for speech production discussed in the previous section. In this model the dictionary is replaced by &lt;em&gt;generative rules&lt;/em&gt; which can synthesize signals in response to instructions consisting of sequences of phonemes… The internally generated signal which provides the best match with the input signal then identifies the required phoneme sequence. (pg. 157)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They go on to discuss the other common features of analysis by synthesis: first, that a “preliminary analysis” can cut down on the number of phoneme sequences that need to be analyzed, and second, that a “control” component can determine the order in which to test out phoneme sequences. The data-driven MCMC approach from &lt;a href=&quot;/quals/analysis%20by%20synthesis/2015/11/10/Yuille2006.html&quot;&gt;Yuille &amp;amp; Kersten&lt;/a&gt; has echoes of this – in their case, different hypotheses are generated by simple cues (preliminary analysis) and then the MCMC algorithm performs a random walk in hypothesis space proportional to the posterior probability of the hypotheses (control).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;methods&quot;&gt;Methods&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;n/a&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;algorithm&quot;&gt;Algorithm&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;n/a&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;takeaways&quot;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the foundational work on analysis by synthesis and is remarkably forward thinking. Even though it’s applied to speech perception here, it could easily be applied to many other areas of cognition (e.g., vision as Yuille &amp;amp; Kersten have already shown). It also seems like there is a lot of similarities to this approach and the increasingly popular idea of training a deep network on low-level features, and then using a structured Bayesian model on top of the the output of that network. The similarity is that the deep network takes the place of a powerful learning system for determining relevant cues, and the Bayesian model does the high level work of constraining and evaluating hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 05:35:12 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/analysis%20by%20synthesis/2015/11/11/Halle1962.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/analysis%20by%20synthesis/2015/11/11/Halle1962.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Analysis by synthesis</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Analysis by synthesis: A (re-)emerging program of research for language and vision</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Bever2010&quot;&gt;Bever, T. G., &amp;amp; Poeppel, D. (2010). Analysis by Synthesis: A (Re-)Emerging Program of Research for Language and Vision. &lt;i&gt;Biolinguistics&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;43&lt;/i&gt;(2), 174–200. Retrieved from http://www.psych.nyu.edu/clash/dp_papers/bever.poeppel.pdf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bever &amp;amp; Poeppel describe the &lt;em&gt;analysis by synthesis&lt;/em&gt; (AxS) approach and how it applies to language. AxS was apparently first proposed by &lt;a href=&quot;/quals/analysis%20by%20synthesis/2015/11/11/Halle1962.html&quot;&gt;Halle &amp;amp; Stevens&lt;/a&gt; as a hypothesis for how speech production works. It follows the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Form a rough hypothesis about the input based on simple cues&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Synthesize a full simulation of the input based on that hypothesis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compare the simulated input to the real input&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the two match, then the structure of 2 is taken to be the true structure of the input&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they don’t match, then some iterative process of error reduction is performed. This approach is motivated by the idea that “it is computationally intractable to go directly from the more concrete to the more abstract representation by way of filters or other kinds of ‘bottom-up’ triggering templates” (pg. 177).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bever &amp;amp; Poepple go on to discuss how AxS is related to the motor theory of speech perception, how it is already being (implicitly) used in many automatic speech recognition systems, how it relates to AxS in vision, and the compatibility with Bayesian models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;motor-theory-of-speech-perception&quot;&gt;Motor theory of speech perception&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;motor theory of speech perception&lt;/em&gt; states that “listeners are reconstructing the articulatory gestures of the speaker, and using those as the trigger for the perception of the underlying intended sequence of phones as though they actually occurred acoustically” (pg. 179). To me, this sounds a bit like the “simulation theory” in theory of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;automatic-speech-recognition&quot;&gt;Automatic speech recognition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They note that automatic speech recognition systems often use generative models, for example of “words-to-waveforms”. This is different from the AxS approach proposed by Halle &amp;amp; Stevens, however, in that AxS uses a model of the articulatory system, while the ASR approaches store “vectors representing [Gaussian] mean and variance of spectral slices”. I suppose this difference essentially makes AxS closer to the motor theory of speech perception. At the computational level, I’m not sure how much this distinction matters, assuming the “fixed” model of speech production is detailed enough to capture the full range of effects that can actually occur when speaking a word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;analysis-by-synthesis-in-vision&quot;&gt;Analysis by synthesis in vision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bever &amp;amp; Poepple reference &lt;a href=&quot;/quals/analysis%20by%20synthesis/2015/11/10/Yuille2006.html&quot;&gt;Yuille &amp;amp; Kersten&lt;/a&gt;, among others, and discuss how AxS has been fruitful in vision. They note that given the wide array of cross-modal effects, if such a AxS process exists in vision, then it is likely to occur for audition/speech perception as well, perhaps utilizing some sort of general-purpose mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bayesian-approach&quot;&gt;Bayesian approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, they say that there is no conflict with the Bayesian approach to implementing AxS. I agree with this; there’s no fundamental difference, using a Bayesian model is just a different way of formalizing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;methods&quot;&gt;Methods&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;n/a&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;algorithm&quot;&gt;Algorithm&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;n/a&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;takeaways&quot;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AxS seems to be a promising approach in both vision and language. However, as I discussed a bit in my notes on &lt;a href=&quot;/quals/analysis%20by%20synthesis/2015/11/10/Yuille2006.html&quot;&gt;Yuille &amp;amp; Kersten&lt;/a&gt;, I don’t necessarily see why the “synthesis” component is so crucial. If that’s what is necessary to compute the probability (e.g., if you are using some approach like Approximate Bayesian Computation), then sure, but I’m not convinced that it is. As long as you can compute the PDF at a particular point, then you can evaluate the likelihood of the data given the model without necessarily needing to created a synthesized version of the image or sound production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in general, my takeaway from the “analysis by synthesis” approach doesn’t so much have to do with synthesis itself, but of the combination of low-level cues to generate hypotheses, and top-down knowledge to constrain those hypotheses. The reason for having this particular approach (as opposed to just doing inference over all hypotheses) is that the space of hypotheses is large enough so as to make it intractable to consider all possible hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 03:55:24 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/analysis%20by%20synthesis/2015/11/11/Bever2010.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/analysis%20by%20synthesis/2015/11/11/Bever2010.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Analysis by synthesis</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vision as Bayesian inference: analysis by synthesis?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Yuille2006&quot;&gt;Yuille, A. L., &amp;amp; Kersten, D. (2006). Vision as Bayesian inference: analysis by synthesis? &lt;i&gt;Trends In Cognitive Sciences&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;10&lt;/i&gt;(7), 301–308. doi:10.1016/j.tics.2006.05.002&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yuille &amp;amp; Kersten argue that vision research should not focus on simple, artificial stimuli (as is what is normally the case). Instead, they argue that real, naturalistic images should be used. However, the reason why they haven’t been used traditionally is that it is not clear how to analyze visual processing on these images due to their complexity. To deal with this issue, they suggest relying on generative Bayesian models as a way to formalize theories of visual processing, and present an example of one such model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;methods&quot;&gt;Methods&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;n/a&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;algorithm&quot;&gt;Algorithm&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their model has two main components: one for bottom-up proposals, and one for top-down validation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We propose an “analysis by synthesis” strategy where low-level cues, combined with spatial grouping ruls (similar to Gestalt laws), make bottom-up proposals which activate hypotheses about objects and scene structures. These hypotheses are accepted, or rejected, by direct comparison to the image (or a filtered version of it) in a top down process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use a model similar to a probabilistic context-free grammar (PCFG) in which non-terminal nodes $i$ has attributes for the model type (face, texture, shading, etc.) $\zeta_i$, the region of the image $L_i$ that the model generates, and the model parameters $\theta_i$. The set of all non-terminal nodes is denoted by $W$, whose prior is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P(W)=p(N)\prod_{i=1}^N p(L_i)p(\zeta_i\vert L_i)p(\theta_i\vert \zeta_i)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the number of non-terminal nodes, $N$, is also a random variable – so non-terminal nodes are themselves another structure that inference is performed over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terminal nodes correspond to the actual image, and have a likelihood of $p(I_{R(L)}\vert \zeta,L,\theta)$ for the particular region of the image that they correspond to. Combining all the regions, the overall likelihood for an image is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P(I\vert W)=\prod_{i=1}^N p(I_{R(L_i)}\vert \zeta_i,L_i,\theta_i)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now given $P(I)$ and $P(I\vert W)$, inference can be performed to compute $\mathrm{arg}\max_W p(W\vert I)$ which corresponds to the most likely scene grammar given the observed image. To actually perform inference, they use “data-driven MCMC” which allows for using bottom-up discriminative cues to make proposals for a “transition kernel”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;K_i(W,W^\prime)=q_i(W,W^\prime)a_i(W,W^\prime)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where each $K_i$ gives the probability for transitioning from $W$ to $W^\prime$ and corresponds to a particular operation on the parse tree. The $q_i$ function is the discriminative proposal function, and $a_i$ is the acceptance function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model from this paper is actually one described in more detail in another paper (which I have not yet read through, only the abstract):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Tu2005&quot;&gt;Tu, Z., Chen, X., Yuille, A. L., &amp;amp; Zhu, S.-C. (2005). Image Parsing: Unifying Segmentation, Detection, and Recognition. &lt;i&gt;International Journal Of Computer Vision&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;63&lt;/i&gt;(2), 113–140. doi:10.1007/s11263-005-6642-x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;takeaways&quot;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generative Bayesian models allow us to build powerful, structured models that may allow us to better capture complex real-world phenomena such as realistic images. While Yuille &amp;amp; Kersten don’t explicitly turn their model of visual segmentation and processing into a theory for visual perception, it certainly provides a foundation that could be used in future work (and perhaps has been – I haven’t investigated this yet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear to me whether there is actual “synthesis” going on in this model. Computing a likelihood function doesn’t necessarily mean that you have to sample from that likelihood. Do they actually syntesize image patches and compare them to the true image? Or are they just computing this likelihood function, without needing to synthesize anything? I do think it is important to have the &lt;em&gt;capacity&lt;/em&gt; for simulation/synthesis (certainly it seems we have this, based on mental imagery) but I’m not sure it’s necessary for actually performing inference. The generative capacity is necessary, perhaps, but “generative” still does not mean that images are being synthesized.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 10:42:19 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/analysis%20by%20synthesis/2015/11/10/Yuille2006.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/analysis%20by%20synthesis/2015/11/10/Yuille2006.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Analysis by synthesis</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Humans integrate visual and haptic information in a statistically optimal fashion</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Ernst2002&quot;&gt;Ernst, M. O., &amp;amp; Banks, M. S. (2002). Humans integrate visual and haptic information in a statistically optimal fashion. &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;415&lt;/i&gt;(6870), 429–433. doi:10.1038/415429a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People get information from multiple modalities – for example, from haptic feedback and from visual perception. Ernst &amp;amp; Banks asked, how do people decide which modality of information to rely on? Or, do they combine modalities, and if so, how do they weigh the respective information? They hypothesized that people perform a MLE estimate of the sensory information based on a weighted average of the information from each modality, and present quantitative fits for this model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;methods&quot;&gt;Methods&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were three different experiments. In all the experiments, they had participants judge the height of a bar relative to a standard stimulus (i.e., judging whether the current stimulus is higher or lower than the standard one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, there were two experiments (visual-only and haptic-only) that they used to estimate the PSE (point of subjective equality) for each modality. These PSE estimates are a proxy for how much uncertainty people have. For the haptic-only experiment, there was no variance in the noise, while in the visual-only experiment, they varied the noise levels between 0 and 200%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third experiment combined haptic and visual feedback, and again varied the visual noise level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;algorithm&quot;&gt;Algorithm&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming the noise in each modality is Gaussian with variance $\sigma_i^2$, then the MLE estimate of the percept is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\hat{S}=\sum_i w_i\hat{S}_i&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;w_i=\frac{1/\sigma_i^2}{\sum_j 1/\sigma_j^2}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming that the ratio of the visual weight to the haptic rate is the same as the ratio between the haptic and visual thresholds (PSEs), or $w_V/w_H=T_H^2/T_V^2$, then the weights are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;w_V=1-w_H=\frac{T_H^2}{T_V^2+T_H^2}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;takeaways&quot;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on these experiments, it would seem that people seem to trade-off between different sources of information depending on how reliable that information is. If a normally reliable source of information (e.g., vision) becomes unreliable, then people will fall back on another source (e.g., haptic).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have two main questions regarding this paper. First, why didn’t they attempt to modulate the haptic feedback as well? Since that was constant, we don’t actually know whether participants optimally trade-off between vision and haptic feedback – only that they seem to appropriately modulate their reliance on visual information. It would be interesting to see if the same effect holds after introducing uncertainty into haptic feedback (perhaps making the participants wear gloves?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I’m not sure the choice of MLE/uniform prior is necessarily appropriate. Why not use MAP with a prior on the types of percepts people are likely to encounter? Even if the intuition is that the prior would be broad enough that it’s essentially uniform (or is actually uniform), it would be better to motivate this and have some discussion about it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 15:11:30 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/probabilistic%20models%20of%20perception/2015/11/09/Ernst2002.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/probabilistic%20models%20of%20perception/2015/11/09/Ernst2002.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Probabilistic models of perception</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bayesian integration in sensorimotor learning</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Kording2004&quot;&gt;Körding, K. P., &amp;amp; Wolpert, D. M. (2004). Bayesian integration in sensorimotor learning. &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;427&lt;/i&gt;(6971), 244–247. doi:10.1038/nature02169&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Körding &amp;amp; Wolpert ask the question: do people account for both the statistics of the environment as well as perceptual uncertainty when engaged in a motor learning task? They proposed three models for how participants could be taking these various factors into account:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Full compensation – upon receiving feedback, participants fully adjust by the difference between their observation and where their finger would have been if there were no lateral shift. This model predicts that the final displacement error will be zero-mean with variance just based on the perceptual uncertainty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bayesian probabilistic – participants optimally combine information about the prior distribution and the uncertainty of visual feedback. This predicts that the final displacement error should increase as uncertainty increases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mapping – participants learn a mapping between feedback and the lateral shift, which essentially means that they adjust by the mean of the prior (but do not take into account perceptual uncertainty) plus uncertainty from “intrinsic processes”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They find that participants’ deviations from the target did change as a function of the perceptual uncertainty, indicating that they must have taken it into account, and therefore ruling out models 1 and 3. Model 2 is consistent with the empirical results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t entirely understand why they expect the slope to be non-zero in the case of $\sigma_0$ and model 3. I think it’s because they say “the uncertainty comes from intrinsic processes only”, but they don’t go into details as to what this means exactly, or what that uncertainty is, beyond saying that if that Bayesian model is assumed, then the visual uncertainty for $\sigma_0$ is $0.36\pm 0.04$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;methods&quot;&gt;Methods&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants had to point to a target. However, they could (in general) not see the movement of their finger while doing so. There were four types of trials:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$\sigma_0$ – exact feedback given at the midway point, and also at the end of the trial (single white dot)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$\sigma_M$ – blurred feedback with medium variance given at the midway point (25 transluscent dots with standard deviation of 1cm)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$\sigma_L$ – blurred feedback with large variance given at the midway point (25 translucent dots with standard deviation of 2cm)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$\sigma_\inf$ – no feedback given&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the feedback was always displaced laterally by an amount drawn from the distribution $\mathcal{N}(1, 0.5)$. So, there was so “true” displacement, as well as random noise in the observation of their finger position. Final finger positions were recorded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also ran another experiment in which the prior distribution was bimodal, rather than a Gaussian centered at 1cm. Participants seemed to adapt to this distribution as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;algorithm&quot;&gt;Algorithm&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal is to estimate a distribution for the true displacement $x_{true}$, based on the observed $x_{sensed}$:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;p(x_{true}|x_{sensed})\propto\mathcal{N}(x_{sensed}; x_{true}, \sigma_{sensed})\mathcal{N}(x_{true}; 1\mathrm{cm}, \sigma_{prior})&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MAP estimate of this distribution is then:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;x_{estimated}=\frac{\sigma^2_{sensed}}{\sigma^2_{sensed}+\sigma^2_{prior}}[1\mathrm{cm}]+\frac{\sigma^2_{prior}}{\sigma^2_{sensed}+\sigma^2_{prior}}x_{sensed}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that $\sigma_{sensed}$ here isn’t necessarily exactly the exact uncertainty from $\sigma_0$, $\sigma_M$, and $\sigma_L$, but a combination of that as well as intrinsic motor and/or perceptual uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;takeaways&quot;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In motor learning tasks, people adapt to the statistics of the world that they are interacting with. They are able to learn about the uncertainty in processes affecting their movement (in this case, lateral movement, but this could also potentially be something like wind or the mass of an object inhibiting movement), whether that be a regular Gaussian distribution, or even a bimodal distribution. Moreover, people take into account sensory uncertainty – both their own (arising from noise in perceptual/motor processes?) and that imposed by the experimenter. Being able to account for this sensory uncertainty could be useful in learning how to deal with distorted perceptions (e.g. angle of refraction when looking into water, perhaps?). In particular, this adaption seems to be consistent with optimal Bayesian integration of prior and sensory uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 10:43:06 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/probabilistic%20models%20of%20perception/2015/11/09/Kording2004.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/probabilistic%20models%20of%20perception/2015/11/09/Kording2004.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Probabilistic models of perception</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Demo: Motion illusions as optimal percepts</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Weiss2002&quot;&gt;Weiss, Y., Simoncelli, E. P., &amp;amp; Adelson, E. H. (2002). Motion illusions as optimal percepts. &lt;i&gt;Nature Neuroscience&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;5&lt;/i&gt;(6), 598–604. doi:10.1038/nn858&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, just create our imports and define a few helper functions to get started:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;%matplotlib inline
import numpy as np
import scipy.stats
import matplotlib.pyplot as plt
from ipywidgets import interact

def imshow(ax, p):
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;Show the probabilities as a function of x and y velocities.&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
    ax.imshow(p.T, origin=&amp;#39;lower&amp;#39;, interpolation=&amp;#39;nearest&amp;#39;, cmap=&amp;#39;gray&amp;#39;)
    xmid = (p.shape[1] - 1) / 2
    ymid = (p.shape[0] - 1) / 2
    ax.vlines(ymid, 0, p.shape[1], color=&amp;#39;gray&amp;#39;)
    ax.hlines(xmid, 0, p.shape[0], color=&amp;#39;gray&amp;#39;)
    ax.set_xticks([])
    ax.set_yticks([])

def uniform(x, low, high):
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;Compute the log probability for a uniform random variable between (low, high).&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
    return scipy.stats.uniform.logpdf(x, low, high - low)

def norm(x, mu, sigma):
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;Compute the log probability for a Gaussian random variable with parameters μ and σ.&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
    return scipy.stats.norm.logpdf(x, mu, sigma)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Define a few options for the prior. In the paper, they used the equivalent of &lt;code&gt;prior1&lt;/code&gt;, but I’m also interested in comparing to a uniform prior and a Gaussian prior with different mean:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;def prior1(vx, vy):
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;Zero-mean Gaussian prior with σ=25&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
    return norm(vx, 0, 25) + norm(vy, 0, 25)

def prior2(vx, vy):
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;Velocity Average (VA) Gaussian prior with σ=5&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
    return norm(vx, 17.88461538, 5) + norm(vy, -14.42307692, 5)

def prior3(vx, vy):
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;Uniform prior between -50 and 50&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
    return uniform(vx, -50, 100) + uniform(vy, -50, 100)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, define the full model. This assumes a thin rhombus, but the prior function and the contrast (i.e., inverse sigma) can be modified:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;def model(prior_func, sigma):
    vx, vy = np.ogrid[-50:51,-50:51]
    prior = prior_func(vx, vy)
    lh1 = uniform(vx, -50, 100) + norm(vy - vx + 30, 0, sigma)
    lh2 = uniform(vx, -50, 100) + norm(vy - 1.5 * vx + 45, 0, sigma)
    posterior = lh1 + lh2 + prior
    MAP = np.unravel_index(np.argmax(posterior), posterior.shape)

    fig, axes = plt.subplots(1, 4)
    fig.set_size_inches(12, 3)

    imshow(axes[0], np.exp(prior))
    axes[0].set_title(&amp;#39;Prior&amp;#39;)
    
    imshow(axes[1], np.exp(lh1))
    axes[1].set_title(&amp;#39;Likelihood 1&amp;#39;)
    
    imshow(axes[2], np.exp(lh2))
    axes[2].set_title(&amp;#39;Likelihood 2&amp;#39;)
    
    imshow(axes[3], np.exp(posterior))
    axes[3].set_title(&amp;#39;Posterior&amp;#39;)
    axes[3].autoscale(enable=False)
    axes[3].plot(MAP[0], MAP[1], &amp;#39;ro&amp;#39;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Original prior, high contrast:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;model(prior1, 1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/quals/notebooks/Weiss2002_files/Weiss2002_9_0.png&quot; alt=&quot;png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Original prior, low contrast:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;model(prior1, 10)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/quals/notebooks/Weiss2002_files/Weiss2002_11_0.png&quot; alt=&quot;png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VA prior, high contrast:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;model(prior2, 1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/quals/notebooks/Weiss2002_files/Weiss2002_13_0.png&quot; alt=&quot;png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VA prior, low contrast:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;model(prior2, 10)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/quals/notebooks/Weiss2002_files/Weiss2002_15_0.png&quot; alt=&quot;png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uniform prior, high contrast:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;model(prior3, 1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/quals/notebooks/Weiss2002_files/Weiss2002_17_0.png&quot; alt=&quot;png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uniform prior, low contrast:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;model(prior3, 10)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/quals/notebooks/Weiss2002_files/Weiss2002_19_0.png&quot; alt=&quot;png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 08:55:41 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/probabilistic%20models%20of%20perception/2015/11/09/Weiss2002-ipynb.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jhamrick.github.io/quals/probabilistic%20models%20of%20perception/2015/11/09/Weiss2002-ipynb.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Probabilistic models of perception</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
